# Rakesh Kumar Patra

## Senior Software Engineer

rakesh.patra93@gmail.com | Github | LinkedIn

#### PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Energetic software engineer with 6 years of experience of full stack development for projects like social-media advertisement, ad-management, tourism and healthcare. Experienced in gathering client requirements and giving it reality with most efficient technical solutions. Also keeps interest in open-source contribution.

#### **TECHNOLOGIES**

| Front End         | Bootstrap, JavaScript, Jquery, React.js |
|-------------------|---|
| Back End          | Ruby, Rails                             |
| Data Stores       | MySQL, PostgreSQL, MongoDB, Redis       |
| Web Servers       | Apache, Nginx                           |
| Operating Systems | Ubuntu, MacOS                           |

#### **EXPERIENCE**

Activate Care | Sr. Software Engineer | BigBinary | Pune, India

Oct 2019 – Present

Activate Care helps communities across the country unify health and social care to improve health outcomes.

Technologies: Ruby on Rails, PostgreSQL, ReactJS, ElasticSearch

I was responsible for building both the front-end and backend features for the app.

- Worked with the PM to build technical plans for new projects.
- Added reusable React components and features.
- Optimized and fixed existing flaky test cases to make it faster.
- Updated documentation of the app.
- Reviewed code of peer developers.

Flipp | Sr Software Engineer | AccionLabs | Bangalore, India

Jan. 2019 - Oct 2019

This app provides nearby deals to customers by collecting the flyers and product prices of stores nearby.

Technologies: Rails 5, Ruby 2.3.3, MySQL, Watir, Circle Cl

I was responsible for working on the backend app for gathering flyers/ads and indexing products from the merchant websites.

- Worked on writing and maintaining indexers, which are libraries to fetch flyers from various merchant websites.
- Built Generators to automate creating files to onboard a new merchant seamlessly.
- Worked on writing indexers to grab product lists and product details from merchant websites.
- Wrote tests for the indexers.

Reach-Labs | Sr. Software Engineer | Mindfire Solutions | Bhubaneswar, India

Aug 2014 - Dec 2018

It's a platform where Users/Celebrities can post content to different social platforms like Instagram, Facebook, Twitter etc to advertise for various brands and get paid for the same. Also monitors and displays the analytics and behaviour of engagement for those.

Technologies: Rails 4.2.3, Ruby 2.3.4, MySQL, MongoDb, JavaScript, SCSS, HTML, HAML, ReactJS, GCE

I played a key role for the API development and admin module.

- Designed API application which was consumed by mobile apps.
- Worked on building and maintaining Admin portal where admins can manage the whole system.
- Worked on migrating apps from Linode server to Google Compute Engine.
- Upgraded Ruby/Rails versions for the apps.
- Implemented various social media integration to the apps to gather analytics from across platforms.
- Worked on Google- Maps api for storing and displaying user's realtime locations to perform geo-campaigns.
- Also worked on building an Alexa skill for campaign reporting, integrated smooth for that functionality and google-cloud-storage for storage.
- Mentored junior developers.

Tripixo, MyDe | Sr Software Developer, CTO | Tripixo | Bhubaneswar, India

June 2017- Nov 2017

This app solves a problem in the tourism sector, like everyday people from different countries/language from across the globe visit different tourist destinations and many of them really don't get enough information and history related to that place. So the app provides voice guides(of different languages) along with transcripts and images for the destinations which assists a tourist to gain facts and information to enjoy the place. It also had another feature to book physical registered guides if someone needs the traditional way.

Technologies: Rails 5, Ruby 2.3, MySQL, MongoDb, JavaScript, SCSS, HTML, HAML, AWS, mailchimp, instamojo

I was responsible for designing the architecture of the whole system to drive the business. I had worked on the backend for APIs of the mobile app, payment integration and admin management portal.

- Built bootstrap website for Consumers where they can learn about the app and can download the Mobile App.
- Build API applications for both consumers and guides
- Integrated payment modules

#### **OPEN SOURCE**

- Built an open-source gem <u>Custom DB Driver</u> to use activerecord like associations across different ORMs like Activerecord(mysql) and Mongoid(mongoDb).
- Built a gem Instagram Graph API which is a wrapper koala gem and provides instagram API integration.

### **EDUCATION**

Biju Patnaik University of Technology | Odisha, India | 2010 - 2014

Bachelor of Technology(Electronics & Telecommunication)